Companies are ruthless right now with
performance. This is Stefan Mai. He was
a senior manager with experience across
Amazon and Meta. And last week I asked
him about the behind the scenes of
managing in big tech. You mentioned
PIPS. Are they just a formality to
create a paper trail?
>> Like at Amazon HR really just wanted to
make sure that it was a pretty savage
culture to be honest. Low performer
quotas, how do they work? It's mostly
like a group survival thing, but in most
cases, what ends up happening is that
>> I also asked him about his career story
growing to senior manager at Meta. What
was the thing that made you leave and
want to join Meta? The second thing that
that kind of bothered me is that Amazon
in general, Meta versus Amazon, what are
the cultural differences that stand out
to you?
>> Probably on average, I'd say Meta
Engineers were a bit stronger, but they
weren't as
Let's get into it. I think the the
things I want to ask you, I mean,
because you were a senior manager in big
tech, I feel like there's a lot that
goes on behind the scenes in managing
orgs. And I thought it would be really
interesting for, you know, all the IC's
out there, all of the, you know, PIP
stuff that happens, all of the stack
ranking, behind the scenes performance
management, and of course, I was curious
about your career. So I guess before we
dig into all that maybe we can start
with Amazon. Can you tell me a little
bit about what you worked on and you
know how you got to Amazon?
>> Yeah. So I I guess for me personally I
was one of those engineers who was like
not very focused on school. I always
wanted to be building and my initial
work was just kind of scattered. I did
consulting and worked at startups. I
didn't really find the technical depth.
And so when I had the opportunity to go
work at Amazon, this is I think back in
2012, u I basically leapt at the
opportunity. It seemed like a place that
they were working on some really hard
problems at scale. Now, funny enough,
Amazon had this reputation at the time.
This was before the New York Times had
published uh this article about people
crying under their desks. Uh but it was
a place that was known for just grinding
down engineers. And I think that's still
true of its uh its branding today. Um,
but I ended up joining the early
advertising group. Advertising for
Amazon now is a gigantic business. It's
one of their most profitable units. It
basically makes up for all the the the
retail lack of profit profitability. But
um I was part of one of the early teams
that was building out self-service
advertising. So they had done a bunch of
work with Proctor and Gamble etc etc.
And my team uh was responsible for
building out uh and scaling the ability
for individual vendors to basically
create advertising and presence on the
site. And it was kind of a weird
situation. Um my manager was was
eccentric, I will say. Uh he was a very
inspiring guy. And I I look back on the
time and and I kind of look through this
lens of what does this mean for me as a
manager? uh but he very much had uh this
idea of how things would be done that I
don't agree with today. And so I
remember I think it was in within my
first week uh my manager uh came down I
think it was like six o'clock we were
all gathered in a conference room and he
said I've got an idea this is what we're
going to build and we're going to work
nights and weekends until it happens uh
and I want to do it by October. Uh so
he's basically committing us to this
death march for about you know six to
eight months at the time and you know I
had just left another job. I had told a
bunch of people that I was going to you
know go work in this big tech company
and I was committed. Uh I think now if
someone had told me that I would have
been like I don't think so. Uh, but I I
really leaned into that and it formed
kind of the basis of of some of my early
development both as an engineer and and
and how I thought about leading teams.
Uh, but it also gave me a flavor for
like what Amazon is like in kind of its
rawest form. And I feel like that death
march is kind of emblematic of a lot of
people's experience at least on the
negative side with Amazon.
>> You went towards the advertising space.
Was that something that you you picked
or was that something that there was a
general pipeline and you were placed
somewhere?
>> No, good question. So, Amazon at the
time wasn't doing kind of general
recruiting. So, basically, you would get
reachouts and you would engage with a
specific org. Uh, and in in my case, the
uh recruiter that I was working with was
spit strictly in advertising. I did have
a choice between multiple teams. Um and
I basically chose the team that seemed
like it had the most growth and most
opportunity. Uh the pitch was pretty
strong and ultimately was a very
important business. Like this was the
beginning of Amazon ad. So um you know
from a career perspective it was a good
choice but yeah I I didn't have an
option to go work on S3 at AWS or
something like that.
>> And so it it looks like it turned out to
be a huge grind. And I saw that you
stayed there for some time. you know,
what was the average work like or was
that just an early death march for you?
>> Yeah, I would say that that wasn't
completely standard throughout my
career. There were certainly times where
things settled down. Um, I' I'd say like
the average was was working hard. I
think any big tech uh job, it's going to
require quite a lot of effort and even
more so if you're ambitious and want to
get things done. Um, so you know, for
me, working 50, 60 hours a week was was
fairly common, but it wasn't always the
case that it was working nights and
weekends.
>> Right. Right. Okay. That's good to hear.
Um, I I saw that you went from, you
know, you grew through the early levels
and then you also transition to
management at uh, Amazon as well. Um,
are there any notable stories from your
growth to an SDM? Yeah. So that was kind
of an interesting transition uh in part
because I guess my level of ownership
and engagement early on meant that in
many places I was the de facto lead for
the team. I guess tech lead probably
would describe my responsibilities
pretty well and I felt like in a lot of
cases I was acting like manager of the
team. My my boss really didn't have time
for a lot of the nicities that normal
managers would provide and so in some
sense I was doing that for the team. Um,
but that title actually was quite a bit
lagging, at least as it felt to me. It
always feels like this for manager
transitions. People were like, "I'm
ready." Uh, and what you don't realize
is how far you have to go. Uh, but um,
you know, I I really pushed to try to
get that title to have those
responsibilities and um, I would say I
probably got it prematurely. Uh, they
should not have given in. Um, ultimately
I think that manager transition is
really fraught. Uh for a lot of people,
they make a ton of mistakes early on.
I'm I'm no different. Uh there's a lot
to learn and in some sense, the support
structure that you have around you is
going to dictate a lot of your success.
Uh I remember for the first year feeling
very uncomfortable, maybe rightfully so.
I was failing in a lot of different ways
that I probably didn't completely
realize. Uh, and it wasn't until, you
know, 18 months down the road that I
started to really get a knack for things
and realize, yeah, this is actually
something that I feel like I can do
quite a bit better than than other
people can.
>> What were those early manager mistakes
that make you say it was premature?
>> I think, you know, management is a
really soft discipline. Uh, you don't
have the same sort of uh output metrics
and things that you can point to that
are obviously yours. And in a bunch of
cases, it's really about storytelling.
It's like uh you know, how do you uh
take account of your contribution to
this team? How did you level people up?
But I think for me, a lot of those soft
skills were missing, at least initially.
Um so, as an example, I don't think I
spent enough time really getting to
understand and know the goals and
objectives of all the people on my team.
This sounds like manager 101 stuff, and
maybe it is. I think I realized at the
time that this was important, but I
didn't know how to do it. I didn't
really know how to break through to
people. I didn't know how to get them to
open up about the most important uh
aspects of their work. And as a result,
I wasn't able to cater both the support
that I offered um as well as kind of the
the work that we were assigning and and
and helping people to find um to the
individual was kind of making a a very
elementary mistake as it as it pertains
to management. I see. Um, you mentioned
getting people to reveal their goals.
Um, do you have any tips for that as a
early manager or for early managers?
>> I think it being a a new manager is very
tricky because in a lot of cases you'll
make that transition in a team that has
seen you as an IC as a peer and the
relationship
is necessarily different. I think a lot
of people think, "Oh, you know, I've got
a good relationship with with a bunch of
other engineers. Um, you know, we're
able to talk about stuff. They'll be
able to be transparent." What they don't
realize is that power dynamic that is
introduced is really corrosive to some
of those bonds. And ultimately, the same
kind of information um is is is not all
that useful. So, it's not enough to know
that, you know, your friend is having a
good time or a bad time. what you really
want to know is deeper questions around
you know what are their career
objectives what is it about the work
that they're doing right now um that you
know that's really dragging on them and
so I think for u new managers the first
thing that I would say is uh being able
to actively listen um active listening
is something that is very familiar to
people who are not engineers um but can
take a while for engineers to learn and
it's basically this idea that you know
when someone else is talking, show your
interest. Um, sometimes people will talk
about subverbals, so you know, oos and
a's and I heard you. Reflect back to
them things that they've said to you so
that you can make sure that you heard it
well and they can feel heard. And then
ask them questions that show your
curiosity and interest. A lot of times
engineers will enter these really
transactional relationships where
they're used to talking in almost like
APIs, but most of the time people aren't
quite like that. And so it's really
important that you are getting people to
open up because in some sense, you know,
the the jewel that you're able to access
is the thing that's going to help you be
an effective manager for that person,
but they're not going to just give that
up to you. Most people aren't um kind of
that well trained. The the API thing
makes me laugh a bunch because um when I
was really early in my career, I treated
my one-on ones as you know, pure
transactional. we're going to go through
this laundry list of things in the most
efficient way possible. And I always
remember people, you know, there's often
this preamble at the beginning of a
one-on-one where you say, "Hey, you
know, how's your weekend?" or, "You
know, what are you doing tonight or
later?" or something like that. That and
I always thought that that was, you
know, a waste of time, but now as as a
manager and just as a more normal
person, uh I see the value in it for
sure. And so, uh that that makes a lot
of sense. You mentioned storytelling. I
think um obviously for managers there's
a lot of value in that and I think also
for IC's too people talk about the
storytelling behind talking about your
work or maybe getting people interested
and getting buy in behind things. Do you
have any tips on how to improve your
storytelling?
>> That's a good question and I agree that
storytelling is kind of like a bedrock
uh essential skill set to develop. I
think, you know, part of it is just
practice. I think a lot of people don't
really realize that they're telling
stories all the time. Um, but they're
not necessarily putting a lot of
attention to it. So, like when you
recall details to someone, it's a story
in some respects. Or, you know, when you
wake up in the morning and have to
motivate yourself to get out of bed,
you're probably telling yourself a
story. And so, I think the first trick
for a lot of people is just to recognize
those moments and start to critique
them. It's like what story am I telling
myself today? I'm going about, you know,
getting to work because, you know, it's
going to give me money or, you know,
this was the most exciting work that I
could think of three months ago. And
while it's hard right now, it's going to
get better. And, um, you know, here's
the trajectory that we're we're headed
to. You know, one of them is going to
help you get out of bed. And the other
one is not all that good. Um, and so
noticing that and being able to critique
it is kind of a first step to developing
your awareness of of the pervasiveness
of it. But once you're able to be
critical of your own stories, then you
can start to practice and and and get
better at at telling them. That was
actually always something that came a
little bit more naturally to me, at
least in some of my peers as as
managers, is that I always love to tell
the stories of my team success. And so
what I wanted to do every few months is
just look back at all we had
accomplished and then paint it in the
clearest picture so that people could
feel proud of their work. It's like a
lot of times we just go to the sit to
the grind and we're delivering things
all the time, but we don't take a chance
to just really reflect on how far we've
come. And being able to say, "Yeah, we
started with a team of two and our on
call was garbage and we really invested
in that and turned it around and with
the extra bandwidth, we were able to
crush it." That can be really motivating
for people. And it also provides this
really great uh foundation for you to
also describe what the future looks like
to be able to say, you know, here's
where we came from, here's where we are
now, and here's how it's going to get us
to the promised land. It's kind of the
foundation of a great inspirational
story. And I think a lot of people, and
I would the average manager doesn't have
a good handle on this. And as a result,
people are kind of wishy-washy. But if
you can have a team where you are
winning and as a manager you get to
define what winning actually is. But a
team that's winning a lot of other
things are downstream of that. Um you
know how people relate to each other
whether they have zero sum mentalities
whether they're getting in bickering
matches or excited about their work. If
you've got a good story and your team
feels like they're winning those things
will come very naturally. On the other
hand, if you don't have that story and
your team doesn't feel like they're
winning, all of those problems are going
to fester and become insurmountable. So,
yeah, I I think the key is is really
about being able to critique the stories
that are already so pervasive in your
life and then use that in your practice
to be able to improve. You mentioned
your manager didn't have time for the
nicities. What was your manager doing
then and how did you have that
opportunity to kind of do that role
before you even uh had that title?
>> So I I guess my manager was a senior
manager and the expectation would be
that he would be managing other managers
but didn't really feel like he should
have hired other SDMs I think is the
title at Amazon or at least wanted to
wait as much as possible. The impression
I got is that this was just a way of
exerting control over product. This is
the thing that he was most excited
about.
um and liked to spend a lot of time
working with design, refining the
product, and making sure that we went to
market with something that he thought
was going to be successful. Um debatable
whether that was the best use of his
time, but um it was unvariably the the
thing that that he was most focused on.
And that meant a lot of things kind of
fell by the wayside that traditionally
an engineering manager and SDM would be
doing. things like, you know, uh
checking on uh the team's uh progress,
uh understanding their career, uh
mentorship, things along those lines.
They just weren't quite as important.
>> So then, if you were to survey the
sentiment of his org or the people that
were reporting to him at the time, do
you think that it would have been really
negative and there was attrition and
people were unhappy with his behavior
like that? Yeah, I had a lot of a lot of
people who were pretty upset about the
situation. I wouldn't say things were
were particularly good.
>> I see. Okay. Um, and so coming to the
end of the Amazon, you know, leg, what
was the thing that made you leave and
want to join Meta?
>> Okay. Amazon, I guess, is a really
special place. Um, I I I speak some of
the negativity on it, but there's
actually some really cool aspects of the
company. It's undoubtedly very
successful. the engineering discipline
is actually very strong inside the
company. There's a ton to learn there
and so I think you know I I don't want
to give the impression that Amazon is
not a worthwhile company to work for. I
think it certainly is. Uh but there was
a few things that that kind of like
stuck out to me after I had spent a
pretty considerable amount of time
there. One is that part of being
successful at Amazon is kind of
assimilating into a a weird kind of
leadership. Uh Amazon calls it their
peculiar ways or at least they used to.
They had a nice little um mascot that
they they had around this. And what you
start to realize is you're a good
Amazonian. You're not necessarily a good
engineering leader or at least it's
unclear if you've spent your entire
career there. And that started to kind
of like fester in me. I wasn't sure
whether I was just overfitting to this
Amazon opportunity and I wasn't sure
whether I was growing much. The second
thing that that kind of bothered me is
that Amazon in general um I think does a
better job of maintaining evenness in
compensation and talent development, but
in in some sense it makes some
sacrifices in order to do that. So like
I remember getting a promotion or maybe
it was a a really high rating at one
point and having no change to my
compensation and I thought well what
what what's going on here? This doesn't
really make sense. That was quite
frustrating for me and I think the
explanation was oh the stock had
appreciated a lot so you know you
already got your your pay and it's kind
of like well that's true of everybody on
the team that seems a little bit silly
>> but the last thing and I you know I
would periodically respond to to
recruiters who are reaching out but uh
when Facebook had reached out I thought
well I'm not a big fan of the product
itself um but I'm a big fan of the
engineering culture in this company and
the team that they had kind of like
pegged me with was a team in integrity
which was basically doing work sort of
on child safety and um preventing
terrorism and and things along those
lines and I thought well this is really
interesting because I mean I had been
working in supply chain at the time I
was doing a bunch of ML work and while
moving Amazon's you know profitability a
little bit clearly had some impact on
people you lower prices whatnot uh it
wasn't the same type of qualitative
impact it could have at another company.
So those first two things kind of
motivated me to look and then you know
the last piece really um was enough to
tilt me into a new opportunity. You
mentioned Amazon's peculiar ways and how
that might be different from what a good
engineering leader is. Are what are
those things that stick out to you where
you thought I have that at Amazon that's
good for Amazon but that may not
actually be the thing that's for a good
engineering leader?
>> All leadership is trade-offs. Like
styles have pros and cons. I I don't
think that there is one best way and so
I don't want to kind of give that
impression. Um at Amazon, one of the
ways that their leadership works is um
built around this idea that the company
for the longest time was very low on
margin. Um you know, it basically made
money by being efficient. It's
operationally very lean. And you'll
actually hear this reverberated through
some of the leadership culture talking
about lean manufacturing and so forth.
And what it usually involve from a
leadership perspective is um each layer
of the management chain just getting
involved very detailed level uh of the
layers beneath them and that even meant
as a line manager that it was almost
expected that I understood what every
person on my team was doing at any
moment. And the benefit of this is
things didn't just happen. U people were
aware of them. they were very uh closely
tracking metrics, understanding what was
was moving around. Um there's a degree
of discipline that's required in order
to make that happen. But on the flip
side, it can be really stifling to
creativity and kind of like the ability
to to work on on innovative new
approaches if in some sense your bath
needs to be queued in to all the things
that you're doing. That was one aspect
of Amazon's culture that I don't quite
understand. until I was kind of out of
it. Uh but that I think limits their
ability to go into new opportunities to
like you know innovate with new products
but with the tradeoff that it's very
effective at kind of like these growth
stage where the the sole purpose in some
sense is just to move 1% on your your
revenue or to drive your cost down by
1%. In those cases that style of
management is completely appropriate. I
think um Kent Beck has this nice
framework. I'm not sure if you've heard
of it, but I think he calls it the three
X's or um explore, expand, extract. And
what he's talking about in those early
phases is that, and this is true of like
a seed stage company where you have
asymmetric upside. So what you're doing
is you're taking a constant tax uh in
the early phases. So you you basically
have a cost just of keeping people
around. But the sole goal is to try to
achieve that breakout velocity to find
that new opportunity that's going to be
worth, you know, 100x. And so moving
really quickly and not constraining
yourself is really important for teams
and companies in that explore phase. And
then if you fast forward to the extract
phase, these are teams where the the
benefit that you could have in the best
case is like a one or 2% improvement,
but you have this catastrophic risk
that's constantly looming. It's why most
companies don't allow employees to just
jump onto social and represent the
company because even though they might
have a banger post idea, they could also
just completely trash the company's
reputation. And so in those cases, you
want to be pretty riskaverse. And I find
that Amazon culture tends to lean toward
the later stages of uh Kent's uh
framework in part because that's how the
company has grown over the past 30 years
or so.
>> Yeah. And at that stage of its growth, I
mean it's a more later stage company. So
it kind of makes sense that it's uh on
the later end of that life cycle. You
mentioned that at some point you
transitioned to working on ML work and
and forecasting at Amazon and I know you
continued to work in integrity is a very
machine learning focused space. How was
that transition for you? Was that was
that challenging?
>> I think in it always is. uh ML is is is
pretty different than traditional SUI
work in ways that are kind of hard to
explain where you know in a typical SU
project you kind of got binaries you're
things are working or they're not you
can sometimes prove it actually whereas
with ML you're oftentimes dealing with
shades of gray it's like a very common
occurrence for people to have bugs in
their training pipeline that they just
don't notice for years and then they fix
them and then get marginally better uh
performance. It's a really fascinating
phenomena, but it means that how you
operate in projects like this is very
scientific kind of very
experiment-driven
and that style of work is or at least
was for me fairly unfamiliar. It's also
a field that has quite a bit of depth in
terms of fundamentals. I found when I
was wanting to make that transition, um,
I was reading a lot of books, I was
participating in Kaggle competitions, I
was building models on the side, like
the goal for me was just to start to
develop that experience so I could be
effective in a in a different uh role.
Um, and I find that, you know, this type
of transition is much more popular these
days, especially with AI. People are
always thinking about, you know, how do
I pivot into AI? Um, but the the kind of
like magic of it in some sense is being
able to really execute. And I think
that's missing for a lot of people. They
really treat this as like a study
session. Like I need to go um, you know,
learn the 101. And the 101 is is
important, don't get me wrong. Um, but
your ability to be effective as either a
leader or an engineer um is also
dependent on your judgment and instinct,
which only can be honed if you actually
go and build something, if you practice
it. So you're saying the thing that
helped you successfully transition was
not necessarily learning those
fundamentals although you did it. Um it
was the experience building the
intuition behind what is improving model
performance and building your own taste
and intuition. Is that right? Yeah, in
some sense I I feel like the key for me
at least was participating in Kaggle
competitions and then finding ways to
work ML into my present role so that way
I would be able to start to get that
experience. There's just a lot of things
that are nonobvious until you practice.
>> Right. What was the motivation for
moving into ML?
>> I always thought that ML was just really
interesting. Um, it at the time it was
obvious that machine learning was just a
very different style of how computers
could work for us and it was seductive
in in some respects. It's like for
someone who had spent and I I coded from
an early age instructing computers on
how to do things, this idea that we
could just kind of like imply basic
basically a program from the data was
really attractive. And it also felt like
a lot of what was societally important
at the time were actually ML
applications. It's like we didn't
completely understand what was going on
there. Um you talk about ranking in in
news feed or uh recommendation systems
or in Amazon supply chain. There was a
tremendous amount of machinery from
predicting when trucks would arrive and
you know whether vendors would would
actually submit inventory on time to
what customers would demand. All of
these pieces fit together in a really
magical way to produce an output that
you know is just pretty forgettable.
It's like the the item arrives at your
front doorstep, but there is just so
much complexity. I think it's quite
beautiful um behind those systems. And
that's true of general software systems,
but maybe not in the same way. I found
ML systems to be particularly
attractive. I guess you going to your
time at Meta. I saw that you got
promoted from a frontline manager to a
senior manager and I think a lot of
people struggle with that that growth.
So I'm curious, you know, what did that
look like for you? What was the story
behind that promotion to M2?
>> Yeah, it's it was a long story. I think
um I got promoted about three and a half
years into my time at uh Meta. I overall
I had I think seven different managers
over my time. So like one every six
months. So it was very tumultuous uh for
a for a bunch of different reasons. I I
think ultimately that held me back and
and maybe part of my promotion story is
actually like how to handle
organizational shifts and and you know
maintain some momentum there. But when I
I I first joined I I wanted to be useful
as quickly as I could which actually fit
very well with what Meta was looking for
Facebook at the time. And so I joined
the on call. I you know I started
writing code. I basically acted like an
engineer and I think both this built a
lot of trust with both the engineers on
my team as well as some of the peer
teams. Um but also made me much more
comfortable with the work than I think
some of my peers who really tried to
stay out of it. Um that is not
sustainable. I don't think that you know
people can do that for a long time. And
in fact I needed to shift my focus to
recruiting. I basically had a blank
check on recruiting uh for my director
at the time. Um, but that base was
really important because in some
respects, you know, how people perceive
you, especially as a manager, is going
to either be a huge headwind or a major
tailwind for for your progression. I
think a lot of people do end up in spots
where people feel like they know who
this person is and where they fit. And
that can actually be devastating for
your career just because it means those
opportunities may or may not be coming
to you. people have difficulty shifting
what they think a person uh is going to
be like in the future. So that was
really important. Um after I I had kind
of like established myself and and you
know shown the effectiveness of our
team, I was uh eventually given an
additional manager who would work with
me and um she kicked ass. She did a
really great job. We we worked pretty
well together. Um, there was a bunch
about that process of of leading another
leader that I really needed to learn.
I'd say it's kind of the same process.
You know, becoming a manager has a lot
of things that just hit you differently.
Um, and you don't really understand them
completely until you sat on the other
side. Because I think there's this
expectation, especially amongst a lot of
line managers that I talked to, that
okay, I know how to lead other people. I
know how to like have impact indirectly.
Surely layering another manager beneath
me is just kind of that same thing,
right? It's that same pattern. Um, and
that the response that I have to that is
like yes and no. Like it is nowhere near
the same degree of difficulty shift from
from making that initial transition. But
I think if you assume that leading other
managers is going to be like leading
engineers, then you are going to fail
very quickly. For a lot of people, it'll
just be mutiny. uh you know your your
managers will find some way to displace
you. I think what people don't realize
is that especially in manager stacks uh
that in some sense you're competing with
each other like it's basically unstated
in a lot of fashion but you know if your
org is not growing the path forward for
some of the managers who are leaf nodes
in this org is actually to take the
position of the people that you know
they're reporting to and in many cases
that person will just leave and you know
someone will take that spot in other
cases you know that person will get
displaced in part because the people
beneath them are far more competent. And
so there is a very weird dynamic that
unfolds amongst managers, leading
managers. And I had a surface level
grasp of this, but there was a lot more
for for me to learn in order to be
effective and also just to add value to
to people beneath me. You know, that
went on for some time. Um that that
transition didn't happen until I had an
org of about 30 to 40 people. Um in
other companies, I guess you you'll
typically see a promotion before then,
but um by that point, you know, I was
basically sitting in calibrations
alongside a bunch of other M2s. And you
know, at a certain point, uh it was kind
of hard to deny that, you know, this
person's doing the job. So that was my
promotion story.
>> The mutiny you mentioned is uh really
interesting. How does that surface in
practice? like how you know how could
someone underneath you kind of you know
usurp you or kind of that mutiny could
come in.
>> I I think that the easiest way you'd see
that is just in skip level meetings the
managers are just griping. They're
saying you know Jim he he's not helping
me out much. Jim doesn't understand my
career. You know Jim's changing our our
road map or our priorities too much. Um,
in a lot of ways people, uh, you know,
they grumble about things that are real,
but some people grumble about things
that are just, you know, reason to, to
try to make their relative comparison,
um, between them and their uh, immediate
manager. In other places, people can get
really sophisticated with this. I I hate
to to make it sound very political and
and maybe we can get into this in a
second. Um but the the way that um
people kind of operate in organizations
can get very creative very quickly. I I
remember having a conversation with my
director at one point and we had two
teams in very different organizations
with overlapping responsibilities. And
to me this sounded like a great test,
right? It's a like a scientific
experiment. Well, we'll let them run
side by side. We'll see who wins and
then you know the company gets the
better benefit, albeit with you know
twice as much resources expended. And
he's like, "Stephan, you could not be
more naive. Let me tell you what's going
to happen." And he was absolutely right.
Uh, these two teams are going to find
ways to undercut each other and fight
with each other inside the organization
that have absolutely nothing to do, you
know, with their terminal goal. And um
the the kind of like noise and friction
and everything else is going to dwarf
any sort of gain that you might get. And
you actually might have those teams end
up in a worse spot than if you just had
one team doing it. That's like not a
reason to say you don't ever have
redundancy in investments, but I think
as it pertains to large organizations,
especially when you're leading other
leaders or even leading very senior
IC's, you have to be cognizant of the
gamesmanship that might be happening
under the covers. And you can definitely
assume good intent. Most people are are
are not doing this because they're evil.
But in subtle ways, people want to move.
They want to improve and grow. And not
all of those things are always aligned
with the organization's best interest.
And your job as a senior leader is to
make sure that you can line those things
up that you can kind of keep people on
this path to delivering value. as a a
manager, especially not just a frontline
manager, but more senior manager. Are
you saying that there is a secret chess
almost where there's a behind the scenes
motives that people have aside from the
business motives that are maybe their
personal career motives and that can
lead to some uh unusual behaviors or
maybe these political behaviors that
you're talking about? I don't know if I
would use the word secret chess because
it seems like much more obvious. Like
generally speaking, most people's
objective isn't to go and make, you
know, Facebook a higher value company.
If if you talk with people about their
objectives, they're vast. You know, some
people they want to get more money. Some
people want um you know, certain
positions or influence. Uh some people
want to work on really interesting
problems. Some people want to work with
certain people. the things that people
are after are many and and they're very
rarely kind of like uh single faceted,
but in as much as people have different
objectives, they're going to do a bunch
of interesting things to try to make
those things happen. It would almost be
foolish to assume that they wouldn't,
uh, you know, if if there is, for
instance, and this would be true for
most IC's, um, an interesting project
that you want to do. Most people have
seen this play out on a number of
occasions. It's kind of like, well, how
do I make sure that I'm on that project?
Well, I might pair up with other people
so that way we can, you know, have a
coalition that is making progress on it.
I might go cookie lick. I might go to
the project and be the first one to go
and lay my name on it. I'm going to
write a post and tell everyone that I'm
at it. So, that's hard to pull me away
from that project. Um, I might try to go
and demonstrate that I'm the best person
for it. but maybe the way that I
demonstrate I'm the best person for it
is by showing why the other people who
might be taking that position are
incompetent or they're they're not
capable. And so you end up with all
these behaviors that kind of happen. And
if you observe people for enough time,
you'll you'll have a catalog of them. Um
but in some sense understanding that
that uh dimension kind of like that
secret chess and then making sure that
you're cognizant of it as you taking
actions is really key to being a senior
leader of any large organization. It
sounds like a lot of these behaviors are
kind of zero sum behaviors. So I could
imagine in a environment of either
shrinking company or stagnant company or
I guess suborg of a company that these
would be more prevalent and am I
understanding correctly that if a
company or an org is growing a lot
there's just abundance so there's a lot
less of this going on because everyone
can get their what they want.
>> Totally. Yeah. I think this is a
fantastic call in some sense. The zero
sum mentality usually happens when the
winning starts to slow down. Uh the org
stops growing, the you know successes
are less obvious and then you know
suddenly people are redefining success
in different ways. It's kind of like
okay well the business isn't doing very
good but our test code coverage is is
you know awesome that really needs to
matter to us now. Well is that true? You
know who knows? But I think it really
points to a couple things. One is the
imperative of of winning that I talked
about earlier. It's kind of like as a
leader, it's your job to make sure that
your team is positioned and equipped by
you to be winning. Um, and the focus on
performance is really kind of like one
of the more fundamental focuses that you
can have. And a lot of other problems
that we're talking about here are
downstream of that. The second thing
that's kind of interesting there is that
as orgs evolve, different leadership
styles are more appropriate. It's kind
of like a mature organization that you
know is maybe relatively flat requires a
different kind of leadership that's more
attuned to some of the ways that things
are going to go wrong than that early
stage where uh you know you you can kind
of like not pay attention like I think a
lot of early Facebook uh leadership was
kind of like this very very talented um
engineering leaders who in some sense um
rode this tremendous wave of growth. But
are those leaders the same ones that are
going to do best during, you know, a
period of plateau? Uh, who knows? Uh,
that's kind of an open question.
>> You mentioned when I asked about what
does mutiny look like, you said that,
and I just want to confirm it was that
M1 would would go to your their skip, so
I guess your manager and say, "Hey,
Stefan is thrashing things. Are you sure
he's good?" kind of things like that
behind the scenes when in meetings you
are not present.
>> I mean, yeah, generally speaking, you
see it in the same way that like uh
disgruntled teams operate. It's kind of
like everybody's making a lot of noise
because they're unhappy. Um
>> and in some sense, the implicit goal for
them is to make a change.
>> And the most obvious change is to change
people. One of the things that is pretty
interesting about being a more senior
leader is that actually your control
over, you know, outcomes is even more
diminished. For a lot of people when
they become managers, they get really
uncomfortable with the idea that, you
know, generally they're not the ones
writing the code. They're not the ones
making the design decision. They need
somebody else to do that, the, you know,
one of the engineers in their team. If
you're a senior leader and one of your
managers is underperforming, what are
your options? You can't step in and go
and do their job for them. That it's
just not an option. And in that case,
that person's going to hate you and they
will leave very quickly. You can give
them some insights, but if you give them
a lot of insights, then they're going to
feel like you're trying to do their job
or they're going to feel like they're
underperforming. And so, as you kind of
walk up the org chart, the ability for a
manager to make an impact on their
immediate reports is is less and less.
it becomes more and more binary action.
It's kind of like, you know, we're
obviously going to have conversations or
how things are going, blah blah blah.
But, you know, if Mark has a an SVP
who's just not making the cut, he's
going to let them go. He's not going to
jump in and coach and try to, you know,
have all sorts of programs to to get
them to the right right level. Of
course, that doesn't apply necessarily
at like a senior manager level, but the
same sort of trend does apply up and
down the the org chart. you've got less
and less levers that you can pull uh to
kind of turn things around.
>> You mentioned manager underperformance.
I'm curious because there were a lot of
layoffs in the past. Do you feel like
managers have uh they're harder to lay
off than uh IC's are? And if so, why?
>> Moving managers around is like
inherently painful. Um usually like when
you put someone in a manager position,
you're accepting that the blast radius
of that change is larger. I again we can
extrapolate from if you grow the the org
like if you're going to bring in a new
VP everybody's gonna know about it like
it's going to be a major and intrusive
change. So that comes with the
territory. Um whether like taking
someone out of that position or not is
hard is in large part whether they're
like loadbearing for that position. if
they've got a really tight relationship
with their team and they know a bunch of
like internal domain pieces and their
cross functional team really isn't
pulling their weight and they're doing a
lot of that, that's incredibly painful.
Um, you know, moving that person out
could be very hard. If on the other
hand, you know, their team actually
doesn't feel like they're adding a lot
of value, their crossf functional team
members are complaining about them, you
know, they might be doing an okay job.
Um, in some cases it can be invigorating
to get someone who's not pulling their
way out of that position. It's part of
why leadership positions in general get
so much attention and why they earn so
much uh money. I is just that the
ramifications in the or chart are just
so large. Uh I I think if the assumption
is like uh during layoffs are you less
likely to get laid off if you're a
manager? I don't think so. Most
companies are going to target a specific
ratio of managers to IC's. And if you
let go of a host of IC's, you don't need
that many managers. They don't just keep
them around. Um, you probably won't see
this if you're looking locally just
because the likelihood of a manager
being laid off is not as high. Um, but
we've even seen recently at, you know,
companies will do what's called a span
of control reduction. and Wilmo try to
say um you know we want to make sure
that managers have 12 reports or we want
to look at the ratio between I think
Amazon did this recently between uh IC's
and managers and we want to increase it
um and in that case uh you know the
managers are the first in the chopping
block so yeah I I don't think it's it's
necessarily easier or harder at least in
a comparable um leveled IC
>> yeah I think I see the occasional
comment that assumes that manage or you
know leaders ers have some special
treatment and they, you know, can't be
fired or it's it's harder. But, uh,
yeah, I agree. I think we've seen that
that is not necessarily the case. You
mentioned, uh, types of leadership per
stage of company and they have there's
different effectiveness if the company's
smaller or more scrappy versus like the
larger companies. I'm kind of curious
about that. what what type of leadership
do you think's most effective when the
company's really small and what type of
leadership do you think is most
effective when the company's very big?
So I think when companies are small you
really need kind of inspirational
executors. Um in some sense it's all
hands- on debt to go and deliver this
thing. There's a lot of excitement.
People want to work for someone who's
impressive, who could do their job. Um,
and in a pinch could kind of step in.
Um, I if you look at kind of company
history, there are plenty of examples of
this. Um, and you know, generally
speaking, you've got these uh SVPs or
directors who were there in the trenches
designing some of the initial features
and that can be uh kind of so
attractive. But I think as companies
scale that becomes harder to pull off
and then those same individuals often
times don't have the same sort of
organizational aptitude that they need.
And so it is like a very different skill
set uh to be able to work in a larger
organization where you know you're
actually not going to have much of an
impact by just digging in and getting
your hands dirty. Um and then you're
there's not going to be a bunch of
momentum behind it. It's kind of
interesting if you think about big
companies they focus is like a precious
commodity and it's very hard to achieve.
People will talk about this in terms of
alignment but you know the biggest
opportunities there are just a few of
them for a very large company but you
have this very large organization who
can look in a hundred different ways and
go in a hundred different directions.
So, if you've got those individuals who
are go-getters and they see an
opportunity and they just run at it and
they're not able to align and, you know,
move information up and down the org
chart, they're actually going to get in
the way. They're going to siphon off uh
energy that could otherwise be put
behind kind of the core initiatives. So
I I'd say that's at least one way that
you might think about what leadership is
most appropriate is kind of like you
know how close to the the execution do
these people need to be but you know
each company is going to transition in
different ways like this was fascinating
for me watching so Amazon the way that
they scaled is by basically setting up
each team and building really concrete
APIs between each team. One of the early
CTOs at Amazon used to call them fitness
functions. I I think he got fired or let
go. But um you know the idea was
basically this team would be responsible
for two or three metrics and they would
they would labor under those metrics and
focus on them um to the full extent. And
the nice thing about this is it meant
that the engineering leadership could
then just assemble these pieces kind of
like you would assemble a system of
APIs. And because each piece was
dependable um you know you can build a
pretty tall stack. And so at Amazon that
worked really well for scaling out the
ordinarily
meant you left a lot of kind of
interesting things in organizational
seams. So like if two teams draw their
lines here, you might be cutting out a
whole lot of value. And also if these
teams need to move to like adapt to a
new change, well they don't know how to.
They're going to be focused on that one
thing that they've been focused on for a
long time. So you know leadership has to
come in and spin up a new team and that
takes a while. They're not very
responsive. So that's one style of
scaling that Amazon is kind of known
for. Meta/f Facebook took a very
different approach. The org is very
malleable. Um engineers move between
projects. Teams don't have really strong
assignments or at least they didn't uh
at a point in time. The code was owned
communally by everyone. And what that
meant is that as uh Facebook scale, they
needed leaders who were able to kind of
work the soft alignment throughout that
organization
without these big boxes that they could
draw around them. Amazon leadership
could benefit from engineers who were
kind of building um an organization on
top of these API primitives. Meta
leaders needed to understand the people
that were involved and what they were
best at and how to move them and inspire
them. And so the kind of person that you
need in each situation is going to be
very different. So there's a bunch of
different dimensions that are going to
change um depending upon company
dynamics. But it is somewhat
illuminating looking at those two
examples just because they while
theoretically at the same level you know
it's two big tech companies ended up in
very different locations from a
leadership perspective. Um and that that
kind of informs at least my thinking
about you know how leadership looks like
across companies. the the caveat that I
want to toss onto the table is you can't
just staff a company with
organizationally savvy people like
eventually it becomes negative sum um at
a certain point you just have a bunch of
sharks who are all fighting each other
and they're not getting anything done so
there's always a balance that's actually
required but like look at um I think
open AI is kind of a good example and
it's it's a company I haven't worked at
so this is observations of their hiring
process and then talking to people on
the inside but generally speaking when
open AAI does interviews they focus a
lot on technical achievements at the
expense of some of those organizational
pieces. So like one of the the pieces of
guidance that we often offer people uh
who are preparing for like project
retrospectives and more of the
behaviorals is to go deep on those
things that are just like really
impressive technical achievements or
hacks and not as much on I built
alignment between six different parties
blah blah blah. Now look, OpenAI has a
ton of politics inside the company. It
it is not immune to these forces by any
means, but they still kind of paint
themselves in that early phase where
they need to be driven by these people
with these uh you know technical uh
achievements as a means of them
attracting the right talent of achieving
kind of their breakout velocity in terms
of um you know what they're able to
deliver. So lots of different dimensions
that are at play. I don't think you can
generalize across these to to any
degree, but you can kind of notice some
trends and and in general um there is
maybe an entropy as orgs get bigger, you
have to have people who know how to
navigate it. It's just uh it's not
something that you can avoid.
>> When I asked you about the promotion to
senior manager, uh you mentioned the
size of your org and that managers were
reporting to you. So, it sounds like
that was a big part of the promotion to
have the scope to be a senior manager.
I'm curious about the skill difference
between an M1 and an M2 in your opinion.
So, I'm curious like if we were to just
imagine I took a random M1 or maybe
yourself and before you were promoted
and you were just a new M1 and I I put
you in an M2 role and you just said have
at it. What are the biggest skill gaps
that you would have had? So I think
being able to like credibly add value to
the people who are reporting to you is
probably the the major one. Um I
mentioned some ways at which managers
have reduced or managers of managers
have reduced um kind of options in terms
of how they can interact with their
teams. And so knowing what those
restrictions are and then knowing where
to exercise the most important ones uh
is something that that's that's hard for
like a straight M1 to to recognize. So
as an example, you know, you might have
a a new M1. They're feeling really good
about their understanding of people.
They go set up skip levels with um you
know, all of their indirect reports and
they ask them, "Oh, you know, what do
you think of Jim? Does he say anything
that you know you don't like? Is he
touching on all of the important career
pieces? And then a week later, Jim's
going to walk into your office and go,
you know, you talked with Jan and you
ask her a bunch of leading questions
around whether I was doing my job or
not. And now she doesn't feel like I'm
being I'm supportive enough. Like, why
did you do that? And then Jan comes to
you and she says, "Well, you know, I I I
really think that you can help me out a
lot with my career because um you know,
you seem to have some really good
insights that, you know, Jim wasn't able
to to see." And so in that moment,
you've just disintermediated Jim. You've
demotivated Jan and you've created a
host of problems that you now have to
solve. It's like a lot of very small
things that you can do as a senior
leader have these magnification effects.
And unfortunately, you don't really
learn about those or you don't learn
maybe the small things um until you've
either observed them yourself uh where
you can kind of introspect and say, "All
right, let me think about all the
interactions I've had with my senior
leadership and where those worked or
where they didn't um or you've got like
a good mental model for how these things
propagate in an organization. Um, but I
think subtle mistakes like that end up
being kind of like uh the easy ways for
an M1 newly in that position to fail.
And the expectation in a lot of cases is
that they're going to make those
mistakes. Just like when you transition
someone from an IC to a manager, you're
expecting them to make a bunch of
mistakes just because it's unnatural.
Nobody really knows about this. You can
read it in books all you want, but until
you practice it, it's a different story.
And so, you know, my leadership chain
when I was doing the M1 to M2 transition
was probably thinking the same thing,
sitting very closely with me. This is
part of the promotion panel. Like, what
kind of support are they going to have?
Does the person who they are reporting
to have enough acumen to be able to bail
them out if things start to go ary? That
sort of thing. But bunch of small
behavioral things would be the first
thing that they would screw up. you
know, longer term, you know, there's
strategy and org design and a bunch of
mistakes that you can make there, but
those small things, especially in the
first few weeks, are enough to sink you.
It's kind of a scary environment to
operate in. To be honest, you've
experienced IC career growth and manager
career growth. I'm curious to compare
and contrast, you know, IC versus
management, I guess, growth paths. What
do you think of the differences between
the two? And also, I'm curious, do you
find that they're both meritocratic? I
often hear that there's some, you know,
cynical takes on some, you know, one
being less meritocratic than the other.
So curious your thoughts.
>> I think at high levels everything
becomes a little bit opaque and fuzzy.
Um, one of the things that always kind
of like was difficult for me to stomach
as a manager sitting in calibrations was
very senior level IC's talked a big game
about their accomplishments, but I
didn't really see the evidence. it
wasn't really obvious whether they were
just around for these big initiatives
that were clearly valuable initiatives
or they were instrumental in driving
them and the same can be said of
managers across the board like that that
it it's really hard to do attribution
and I think over a long run things are a
little bit more obvious like if you have
a manager sit in a role for four years
and they continue to produce success
it's kind of undeniable but on a half to
half basis
It's pretty dubious. So, I could see why
people would feel that way. I think for
IC's, especially when you're like sixes,
maybe sevens, um it's a little bit more
apparent to an external observer whether
they're doing that or not. I think for
an M1, you can usually look at their
team, if you look at it holistically, if
you look at some of their deliverables
and make a pretty good assessment. But I
don't think someone who's outside of
their leadership chain or not involved
in that minutiae would be able to
recognize it as clearly at higher
levels. I I think that there is there's
a bit of unaccountability for a lot of
management. Um this is true in the stock
market. It's kind of like hard to assess
whether you know a leadership team is
any good or not. You really don't know
until you watch it for a while and then
you know somebody might spin up a really
great story to say you know it was
macroeconomic conditions that sunk my
company not you know I failed to
actually recognize that my customers
were slowly walking away from me. That's
true I think at the highest levels. Um,
and I think it can be quite frustrating
for people who are kind of sitting at a
spot of limited visibility with a a
group that is really hard to kind of tie
directly to any particular deliverable
and go this is fair. You you want it to
be as fair as you can. Um, but I think
at a certain level it is it's difficult
to have the data.
>> I see. So, the the early promotions are
the most easy to verify and fair and the
higher level ones are a little bit more
I mean, I'm sure there are fair ones as
well, but you're just saying it's a lot
easier for there to be optics coming
into play. Um, narratives and stories
that are kind of hard to tell what
exactly is going on and who deserves
what. Is that right?
>> Yeah, I think it's a good summary.
>> I see. Okay, cool. Um, I think one thing
I was curious to dig into is that, you
know, knowing that you've been at Meta
and you've been at Amazon and you you
had a fair amount of time at both, I
thought it'd be interesting to kind of
ask you the the pros and cons of each or
at least your personal experience. I
know these companies are very large and
you know some people have great
experiences in a small team and others
have bad ones within these companies.
But I'm curious when you think about
Meta versus Amazon, what are the
cultural differences that stand out to
you?
>> So I think Amazon is disciplined and I
think this is a a major strong point.
Um, I felt like in general if you really
wanted to reach the height of very
structured engineering design, you
probably find that more likely in an
Amazon review than you would at Meta. I
think probably on average, I'd say Meta
Engineers were a bit stronger, but they
weren't as disciplined. And that meant
that, you know, design reviews and
things along those lines were a bit more
fuzzy and and kind of handwavy um than
they were at Amazon. It also was a place
where things were a bit more
predictable. Uh partly because the
business just moves slower, but partly
because you can depend on other teams to
kind of meet certain SLAs's and you know
they're you can page them if they're not
doing the thing that you want. Whereas
at meta, somebody's work isn't isn't um
you know living up. You got to go make
that change yourself because he's
working on photos now. He he hasn't been
working in that code for for months. Um
so that that can be a little bit
frustrating. I find that a lot of people
who transition from Amazon to Meta in
particular find that unstructured
environment that that's so endemic of
the culture to be pretty paralyzing.
They like don't even know how to
operate. And in some ways that's good,
in some ways that's bad. Um, at Meta,
the the main thing that I saw as kind of
like a major positive was just how open
and collaborative the company is. Um, I
thought it was amazing how engineers on
my team were working with orgs that were
completely across the the company on
various things. You know, we might be
working with a researcher in in Paris on
some sort of image model and then, you
know, some infro was being built out of
London and for the most part I as a
manager wasn't even involved in setting
up these collaborations. People just
found each other and they worked
together which I thought was super cool.
I also really like how at Meta there's a
very acute focus on people and kind of
like empowering people to make
decisions. Uh Amazon has a really very
processoriented mindset. They they talk
about mechanisms. So like when something
fails they want to try to introduce
process to prevent the failure. At meta
it's more likely that someone will go
well we learned our lesson u you know
we'll make sure it doesn't happen again.
Now look, that has its downsides. Like a
lot of Facebook's privacy issues are in
some sense its inability to contend with
the same process that Amazon Amazon does
incredibly well. But it means it holds
um you know the the culture back in a
lot of cases. Like one of the things
that was very surprising to me working
in ML at Amazon is how hard it was to
get access to data. Data is the
lifeblood of ML and AI applications. And
in a lot of cases there aren't actually
these privacy constraints, especially
for public data. But at Amazon, you had
to go and build your own data lake and
go and pull everything into your Spark
data warehouse. At Meta, that data
warehouse existed and everyone used the
same one. So you didn't even have those
same challenges. So the there two
companies that I think have very
different approaches. I tend to prefer
Meta's approach, especially as it
pertains to leadership. Um, but Amazon
had some things that I definitely missed
as I made that transition. And there's
clearly reasons why it worked. Like
there are some individuals where I talk
with them for five or 10 minutes and I
go, I think Amazon's a better fit for
you. You know, accepting all the the
other externalities of an actual
position, I think you're going to like
it more um than you might the chaos
that's usually a meta execution. Having
been a manager at each company, you
experience the performance system
intimately. What about comparing and
contrasting the performance systems at
Meta and Amazon?
>> I'd say they're pretty close to be
honest. I think everybody's kind of like
descending into the same valley in terms
of optimality. What you basically have
is like a very public kind of publicized
process wherein uh ratings are
established and handed out to reports.
This is things that managers will talk
about and and we'll kind of hit on
external pieces. And then you've got a
more private usually restricted to
higher levels process wherein you're
trying to decide where to make
investment like at Amazon there's this
top tier designation and at Meta there's
uh additional equity or discretionary
equity um which is basically trying to
say you know who are like the real winch
pins in the organization that we want to
invest in to make sure that we're
successful long term and I think the
important thing for both companies is to
make sure that people feel like the
process rewards performance s um that is
that perception is like incredibly
important. I did an estimate. I went
through and I kept time of all the
different activities and and managers
and preparing for PSC and basically
said, you know, here's how much we spend
per employee on PSC processes. And I
think there's one takeaway to this which
is like this is wasteful. Like how dare
we spend $15,000 per engineer? We should
be building products. But I think it's
easy to miss the forest for the trees
there that the integrity of the
performance review process is the whole
ballgame. If you get that wrong and
people don't believe the process is
going to produce outcomes for them,
they're not going to perform. And in
some sense, you know, the financial
rewards and promotions and everything
else, you need to put as much effort,
even if it's just a ceremony that
doesn't actually do anything behind the
scenes, you need to make it very
believable and credible to people. Now,
I think both companies do do a lot of
diligence to try to maintain the
integrity of the process. Like I think
it's valid. Um, but I did find that Meta
was willing to really go to bat for say
the upper quintile as opposed to Amazon
where I think partially due to frugality
and partially due to kind of this
fairness, they really were willing to
just really double down on on top
performers. like um there would be
engineers and people in my organization
who would clear twice as much as their
peers just because they had gotten so
much additional investment in equity in
part because we knew that they were very
important and they were going somewhere.
At Amazon that's pretty uncommon. You
don't see that as much and they they
would find some way to try to pull that
back. They are a very frugal company.
>> Yeah. I remember when I I worked at
Amazon briefly and one of the leadership
principles was frugality and I I never
uh I never liked that one but uh nobody
does.
>> Yeah, it's a horrible one.
>> Um you mentioned the additional equity
or discretionary equity or it was called
top tier at Amazon. Um how does how do
those conversations work? Is it derived
from the performance ratings or does you
know directors and senior managers kind
of get together? How does that decision
come to play?
>> Yeah, I mean this usually gets it gets
driven by like the VPs and directors of
an organization and how much they choose
to involve the you know different
managers and making that decision
varies. Um you know you'll know if you
have a lot of trust if they come to you
and go hey who deserves this? Um I was
in that position regularly in part
because my or chain was constantly in
flux. Um, but you know, I I might not
have been in that position quite as
frequently if people were able to
actually keep track of my org because
they actually had a boss, you know, who
was consistent. But you know, what
they're really trying to do there is
just figure out kind of a who's got
trajectory. Uh, like who is the rocket
ship? Even if you had like a I wouldn't
say nling, but like a a stellar but not
exceptional half. Uh, but it was obvious
that that was going to keep going. Uh,
that was a criteria. I remember at
Amazon they talked about kind of I think
there was two dimensions. I don't
remember the exact ones but but growth
was definitely one of them. And then the
the second piece and I think this
actually plays a lot is kind of like how
replaceable is this person if they walk
away tomorrow is that going to break our
organization. Um in some sense getting
into those positions can be very
lucrative just because you know they're
going to in some sense try to put those
golden handcuffs on you as tightly as
they can if the or depends on it. like
the the companies generally speaking
know how to avoid completely
embarrassing themselves with attrition
and sometimes the the lever that they
pull is just financial. Um but yeah most
of the time they hope that it's more
than that.
>> You know with some of the the layoffs
that kind of happened in the past there
was the there's mentions of lower low
performer quotas and I'm kind of curious
is that something that you experienced
when you were working at these companies
and how does they how do they work?
>> Yeah, definitely. I I think every
company is going to have this. Every
company that is of scale. Um you might
not see this at very small companies but
the idea being uh there is a lot of
gaming of performance and you'll notice
this like I'll I'll refer to PSC so uh
Meta's performance review process where
you know suddenly the half that seemed
pretty good or maybe okay seems like it
was world shaking you know as people
were writing their reviews about it and
then every single achievement is just
mindblowing and there's this inflation
that happens in everyone's assessment
and ultimately
that's not true. It just can't be true
on average. So a lot of companies will
have you know some sort of uh overall
distribution that they're trying to
target and in order to maintain high
performance they necessarily need to be
letting some people go. Um managers
don't like letting people go. I don't
like letting people go. It is very
uncomfortable. And so you have to beat
people and make them do it. Um, and it
it's mostly like a group survival thing,
but in most cases, what ends up
happening is that, you know, people
check out or, you know, they decide that
they want to go do something else. And
if you're not, you know, reasonable with
with kind of acting on that, um, then
the team starts to suffer. You notice
that that person's not pulling their
weight and, you know, you're you're
going to start to check out, too,
because it doesn't seem fair any longer.
So, quota wise, the numbers will vary.
Like for a lot of companies it's you
know somewhere between like seven and 15
sometimes it can be as high as 20% where
they're going to try to put you in that
lower bucket. At uh Amazon it was like
needs improvement and at Meta it's like
meets some or meets most. And the idea
there is that amongst that bucket they
were expecting some of those people to
not meet the cut. And that's again just
statistics. Um, but that's usually when
like the pips would start to get
engaged. And managers would fight
aggressively to try to keep their people
out of those buckets. And most of this
is saving face. Like here is the worst
scenario for you as a manager. This ends
up being heartbreaking. You work with a
team. You guys kick ass. Everybody works
really, really hard. And then at the end
of the half, after you've told everyone
how much ass they've kicked, you get
instruction from your director that
somebody's got to be in that low bucket.
and now you got to go change your tact.
You got to go back to that person and
say, "No, actually, you know, you didn't
kick ass that hard. Um, that wasn't even
acceptable." And so those sort of like
egg on the face moments are what most
managers are afraid of. And they try
their damnedest to try to prevent those
situations. The reality is a better
circumstance would be the manager is
aware that somebody may be in the, you
know, lower quartile and can message it
appropriately. That way they're not
surprised, you're not surprised. the the
the kind of like structure works fairly.
But if you've got a lot of immature
managers or just relatively new or maybe
they just don't see it clearly, then you
end up with lots of situations like what
I just described where people have to go
mayo with their reports and honestly for
everyone involved, most of which the
actual person who's receiving that news,
uh it can be devastating. So it's pretty
bad.
>> You mentioned PIPS. Um, I I'm curious.
Do you do you think that they they work?
And, you know, were there any
differences between PIPs across the
companies? This is based off that Reddit
thread. I think someone asked, are they
just a formality to create a paper trail
or can people actually get out of a PIP?
So, people can definitely get out of a
PIP. I think PIPs are first and foremost
a legal paper trail, but in order to
maintain credibility of that legal paper
trail, people have to make it through
it. If you just create this process
wherein you just create a paper trail
and nobody makes it out of it, that's
not really going to hold up uh legally.
So at some level it needs to be fair. Uh
most of the time HR is moderating this
and HR's appetite to advocate on behalf
of the employee in these cases is
variable. So like at Amazon, at least
while I was there, HR really just wanted
to make sure that you were checking the
boxes. It was a pretty savage culture to
be honest. in in you know most cases
you're setting expectations with an
employee and saying here's what you need
to do and if they make it then they can
turn it around and if they don't then
then they're gone. It needed to be
reasonable but the manager held a lot of
discretion on you know whether they
wanted to pull the trigger. Now again
most managers don't like firing people
so their preference is actually going to
be for you know someone to go into PIP
and then recover. And so in a lot of
cases, if you are the person on the
other side of a pip, your manager could
legitimately be rooting for you. They
they're not just lying to your face, um
but you know, whether their hands are
tied or not is up to um you know, some
other power in some cases. Uh for meta,
I noted in a lot of cases that HR
really, really, really wanted to make
sure that we had exhausted kind of every
uh avenue before letting someone go.
This is probably not true of modern
meta. Uh but it was true. um several
years back and in part because they
really wanted to protect their
reputation as an employer and so you
know I' I've had engineers who just had
completely checked out and HR was asking
questions that really didn't make sense
and um you know in a lot of cases this
person would probably not object to the
way that we would summarize their work
like uh it's not always just like a
completely crazy occurrence but
sometimes companies will opt to try to
be overly accommodating uh to the
employee. I I hate talking about this in
some respects because it sounds so like
cold and calculating, but the reality is
just at the largest level, companies
have to reward performance and they have
to be, you know, uh sensitive with how
they're they're making their their
resources. And as a result, you know,
terminations are are part of the
picture. And it's important that
companies do it fairly uh with
sensitivity to the people involved. Um
but they have to do it otherwise the the
company won't exist very long.
>> You conducted over 500 interviews across
your time in big tech and you also have
Hello Interview which is an excellent
service for interview preparation and
many other uh resources for people in
the industry which one my roommate said
it was like the best thing that he used
in his prep and he got an offer at
Anthropic. So, every time I'm
interviewing you or Evan, he's he say,
"Oh, it's it's those guys. I love their
product." Um, but I wanted to ask you
about interviewing because I felt like
you might have something uh interesting
to say. With the the rise of these AI
cheating tools and, you know, LM
assistants, I'm curious, you know, how
much do you see that that coming up when
you're either helping people prepare or
maybe you're just in the the space
thinking about interview prep? It's kind
of funny because like as it pertains to
interview prep, our incentives are
mostly aligned like uh you know for the
candidates we want to help them to
succeed and so them cheating at like
mock interviews for instance doesn't
make a lot of sense but surprisingly
we've seen it happen on a few occasions.
I guess the the the situation is
probably like they're trying to like
test out their setup to see if somebody
will notice. Um so like you'll hear uh
one of our coaches reached out. said,
"The guy's talking to his friend in the
background, like, you know, what do what
do I do in this situation? It doesn't
make any sense." Um, remote interviews
have always been a little bit cheatable.
I think the existing tools make this
horrible. Um, recruiting teams seem to
be modestly aware of it. I think they're
overly dependent on some mechanisms that
probably aren't completely effective. So
like in browser uh interviews they're
looking at whether the the page has
focus or whether there's copy and paste
activity which is like yeah I mean the
least sophisticated people you will
definitely catch them and surprisingly
they do like um so they're they're
clearly weeding out um some people but
to be honest I feel like a lot of
interviews are going to change in part
because the role is shifting. It's like
the way that software engineering is
going to work in the future is pretty
different than how it did you know over
the past two decades and as a result it
seems kind of crazy if the interviewing
itself doesn't adapt to it. We see some
companies trying things here. So like uh
they will have assignments that allow
you to use AI which is theoretically AI
proof or they'll choose questions that
AI routinely gets wrong and you know try
to be robust in that way. Um but I'm
more optimistic in the challenges and
assessments evolving um than I am in any
of kind of the anti-cheat stuff. Now the
the sad part about this is companies are
ruthless right now with performance. Um,
people who cheat in the interviews might
get the role, but like that cheating is
not necessarily gonna pan out when you
actually get the job. So, you know, I I
don't have any formal accounting of
this. I don't know many cheaters myself,
but, you know, there's plenty of people
who find themselves on the the rough
side of their performance review shortly
afterward, which I don't think serves
anybody's purpose. I
>> I'm curious because I imagine a Algo
interview is more easy to cheat than a
system design one. Do you see any
differences in I don't know maybe the
growth of Algo interview signups is like
lower lower than the growth of system
design signups or something like that or
anything that might make us uh infer
that cheating has any impact on the the
future.
So I think people are leaning or
companies are leaning more heavily into
design interviews and that doesn't
necessarily mean like system design
which I I think is more more um
standardized across big tech but also
like lower level design um being able to
reason about uh you know classes and
coupling and um you know various
interactions between subsystems and it's
interesting because in some sense the
quality of that design ends up being
loadbearing in like an AI coded world
you being able to come up with good
abstractions and reason through them is
more important. So definitely are seeing
that shift. I wouldn't say I've noticed
any really acute departures from coding
interviews themselves. Like people have
been calling for the demise of leak code
for forever. Um it actually serves a
pretty useful purpose. It it works for
companies. As much as people want to say
interviewing is broken, I think, you
know, it's painful. It's very painful.
But broken is probably a step too far in
part because it's serving company's
needs up until this point. And so I
think it's a bit premature to to assume
that, you know, that's not going to be a
part of the the interviewing process, at
least in the the short to midterm. If
someone was hellbent on passing OpenAI
or anthropic interviews, what's the
optimal game plan from your experience
at Hello Interview?
>> I think it it varies. those companies
are are looking for depth. OpenAI was
notorious for asking the same questions
in basically every interview. I do not
do not know why they were doing this.
Um, but going deep on kind of the the
functional areas uh that they tended to
ask around uh was was a pretty effective
preparation strategy. That's not to say
you could just memorize solutions. The
interviewers are far more clever than
that. Um, but you can get uh you know a
step up if you actually knew
approximately the the areas that they
were in. Um the behavioral and
retrospective interviews end up being
really important uh for these companies.
They really want to see like have you
walked the walk and I think how you
represent yourself and how you talk
about that work also ends up being
really important. Um some of this stuff
can be really hard to do introspectively
as an individual. like being able to
actually talk to a friend or someone
else who can tell you here's how you
came across like here's the vibe that I
got from you uh can be really helpful in
refining your presentation and in
particular the thing that I mentioned
earlier was just moving toward the
technical accomplishments and less about
how you massage the organization to make
things happen. I think for a lot of
people the crowning achievement of
their, you know, staff engineer career
at, you know, big tech is they wrote
seven docs and then got six different
teams to align and then finally wrote
five lines of code in addition to like a
100,000 that were written by junior
engineers. And it's like that was hard.
I know that that worked deeply, but
these companies don't look at it the
same way. And you have to recognize that
in order to to really nail it. I see.
Coming to the end of the interview, I
wanted to ask you some career
reflections, things just looking back on
everything so far. Uh kind of reflect on
some of the things that you've learned.
And so I saw that, you know, in your
resume, you worked in both of your
stints in big tech, you stayed in the
roles for quite some time, maybe around
four years or or longer. And so I'm
curious your thoughts on job hopping
quickly because that is advice that a
lot of people give. What are your
thoughts on job hopping? I think if you
look at the data for people who are like
really ambitious in lower levels, moving
around usually has a lot of advantages.
It's going to if you think back and I'd
love to actually hear your reflections,
but if you think back in your career,
usually those moments of growth are when
you're most uncomfortable. It's like
it's a new scenario, a new environment.
You've got to go and generalize your
skills and you're you're learning a
bunch. And so it it's not just the
hopping itself. It's mostly just
immersing yourself in new environment
that can lead to that growth. So it's
hard to say no to that. I personally
have not really subscribed to this in
part because the motivating factor for
me is going really deep on something.
Like I find that after 2 years now I'm
at the level where I can actually start
to uh you know really make an impact and
those are the parts that are just the
most rewarding for me from a career
perspective. So it kind of depends on
what you're after. Now, at the higher
levels, moving around at a high
frequency is a pretty bad sign. It's
just like it's very hard for you to get
deep enough to have a real impact, to
build the relationships, to understand
the domain just to be effective. And so,
you know, generally speaking, if people
are moving every 18 months or two years
and they're in a really senior position,
as a hiring manager, I'm secondguing and
I'm trying to wonder, I'm going to
invest for a year just to get you ramped
up and then you're going to go move
again in six months. That can be a tough
pill to swallow. For a a mid-level hire,
that that's a pretty decent tenure. Um,
but for a staff level engineer, I'm
second guessing it. So, um I' I'd say
from a career perspective, um early on
moving makes sense unless you're just
really excited about the work,
especially if you're not excited. Yeah,
go go go get a new job, man. Um but as
you, uh as you get more senior, it pays
to find some places that you can
actually put down roots. And it really
helps when people can sense that that
you're you're here to stay and you're
wanting to to really make some changes.
>> Definitely. Yeah. And I think what
you're saying about job hopping not
being as effective later makes a lot of
sense too because for instance a lot of
what you talked about in being a
successful senior leader either as an IC
or as an EM came through influence and
credibility and your ability to get
people to go in a certain direction. And
that's one of those things that I mean
if you just show up somewhere you can
build credibility. You can always
rebuild credibility but it is one of
those things that um as you have it's
like a snowball. It keeps getting bigger
your credibility in the organization
you'll be able to move people a lot uh
easier. So, you know, people who are
early in their org have a
disproportionate amount of influence
because of their um time in the role and
what they've done already and what they
know.
>> Totally. I want to add one thing to that
that there is a trap which which you can
have and that snowball that snowball
becomes a shackle for you. There are
certainly some very senior engineers who
become known for that system that they
created and as much as they try to go
and extend or move in new directions,
everybody knows them for that thing and
they're stuck there. Um, that can be a
real career trap for people. So, a good
question to ask yourself is how
comfortable you are. It's great to feel
like your work is rewarding, but if you
don't feel like you're being challenged,
even if you're really senior, it may be
that it's time to time to move. Uh, and
part of it might be that you just got
stuck in a hole. Otherwise, that
snowball is going to work in your favor.
>> When you think back to your career and
when you felt the most growth on average
looking across everything, when would
you say is the time that you grew most
and why? I I'd say it's mostly around
kind of those transition periods where
I'm in a new space and learning
something and then also applying it.
Those are usually the places where you
can battle test and like stress test
your your own skill set and know what
what's actually durable and and what was
was fake. Um but it's also a place where
you know there's new stuff to learn and
adapt and kind of grow. Couple pivotal
moments for me moving to Facebook was
was huge for me at least from a
leadership perspective was stretched in
ways that I wasn't expecting. There's
also a lot of stress in the company at
the time which was was interesting. I'd
say um pivoting into a more ML focused
role um was a big shift for me and I I
felt like I had a lot to prove. So it
brought a lot of uh external pressure
which which I appreciated um and it gave
me a chance to to really go and kind of
shine. Um and you know other career
growth happens in like much smaller
durations like um it's interesting
looking back longitudinally like I feel
like a lot of my effectiveness both as
an IC and a manager is partially due to
my ability to write effectively. I
learned a lot of my writing at Amazon.
Amazon's known for their writing
culture. Some of it's just actually a
complete waste of time. People just
nitpicking the most stupid stuff. But it
is a company that that really does
encourage good writing which means good
thinking at some level and that has
stuck with me. It wouldn't be like a
moment that I would notice but that
continued practice uh was really
beneficial for me throughout my career.
So those are some of the things that
really stand out
>> on the topic of writing because I I know
it's really important. I'm just curious
what would be your top tip if there's
some you know IC or EM you're saying hey
you need to improve your writing. What
would be the thing? My main thing would
be learn to be a critic first. Go and
figure out what it is you like or
dislike about writing. Go read a doc,
figure out what hits you on the head,
what doesn't. Go and scan it. You know,
see if you can get the big picture in
just a few seconds. Go look for points
of like imprecision or, you know, places
where the the logical conclusions are
well supported. Um, those are all going
to be things that are going to help you
much like I talked about earlier that,
you know, generally understanding, you
know, what what separates good from bad
helps you to make sure that you're
focused on the good. I know when I wrote
first wrote some docs at at Amazon, I
got a bunch of negative feedback and I
thought they were great. I thought they
were awesome. It's kind of like one of
the the the writing exercises they do is
called a PR FAQ, a press release, and
then a frequently asked questions. And
the idea is like get me excited about
that thing that we're going to deliver.
Go fast forward all the way to the end.
And then if you can do that, then
everything before it is worthwhile, but
if at the end you can't really sell it
to me, then it probably wasn't
worthwhile to begin with. And a lot of
PR FAQs at Amazon start with, oh, we
will have a single pane of glass or like
one screen where we can go to to get
everything that we need. And nobody's
excited about that. they're excited
about, you know, 50% reduction in time
spent or, you know, being able to go and
and hire this new person or or whatever.
Um, and being able to look at yourself
and go, "Wow, that was just boring."
Like, what what I was explaining, if I
wasn't kneede in it, nobody would be
excited is kind of the the first step to
to good writing.
>> I see. So, if I'm understanding, it's
hone your taste as a reader first and
that will let you uh critically reflect
on your own writing and improve it
>> and then practice, practice, practice,
practice.
>> I mean, at this point, you've you've had
a lot of success at Meta. Most people
never grow to the level that you grew
to. What motivates you in your career
now, too, because you also you left to
go to a startup. Yeah. What is your
motivation?
>> I really like working on interesting
problems. I like working on things that
I can tell my kids about and then, you
know, them feel like it it's meaningful
to the world. And I like working on
things that I think are are kind of
setting the stage for the future. And so
I always have kind of a tilt toward
those objectives and all that I'm
working on. I think for me the, you
know, relentless march up the career
ladder is secondary. It's not to say
that like money isn't important. It it
clearly is. money powers everything. But
I had a point in my career where that
was that focus on getting promoted and
moving through the ranks was very
important. And I think what I realized
eventually is just like, okay, you're
you're kind of there or at least you're
at a place where, you know, maybe this
will be the the cap of where you're able
to achieve. What's next? And if you can
finally ask yourself that question and
then work backwards and ask, okay, well,
if I want to get to that thing, why not
now? what's keeping me? And for me, for
the longest time, it was I want to start
a business. I think that would be really
fun. I would learn a lot and it's a
great way to impact the world. And I
gave myself all sorts of excuses for,
you know, more than a decade. And
eventually it was like, you're just
lying to yourself. You're putting this
off. And so that that was what was the
impetus for me in leaving big tech and
and and building a business. Um, but
also as kind of the animating force for
me going forward is just trying to look
to that next piece. You know, what what
is it that I'm really after here?
>> And then last question, if you could go
back to yourself when you had just
graduated college and give yourself some
advice, what would you say?
>> I think for me, I probably could have
been better about finding mentorship. I
think I did a lot of it alone and
ultimately if I had found someone like
myself and you know asked them three
questions I probably could have saved
myself months of of toil. There was a
few moments where I put together plans
where I basically said hey I'm going to
take stock of where I'm at try to figure
out where I want to go and then you know
put together a checklist like I have one
such plan somewhere in my dropbox from
ages ago saying you know I I want to get
into ML. This is this is where I want to
go here. here is my plan. Uh those kinds
of things have paid like these
incredible dividends that continue to be
underemphasized by me even to this day.
Um most people don't have that level of
agency to kind of like just figure out
where they want to go and then go and
take it. But the world is very malleable
to to those kinds of plans. I remember a
pretty uh interesting moment. And it was
actually shortly after I had gotten
promoted to to senior manager and I went
to my boss and director at the time and
um and I basically said, you know, here
are the things that I'm going to get
done. Um you know, and it was a long
list of things that I didn't know how to
do to be honest. I was kind of like,
this is what I think I probably should
be doing now. Um but I'm going to like
figure it out like this is this is my
list. And he recalled later to me, I
think shortly after I had left, that
that moment was when he knew that I was
going to be successful in this new
position. Uh because for a lot of people
that lack of agency is what holds them
back. It's very hard to instill.
Although I think there are some
practices that you could probably go
through in order to build up your own
agency. But if you just force yourself
to come up with a plan and ask yourself,
what do you really want and what are the
steps to get there? in a lot of cases
that is going to have a huge uh gradient
on on your ability to grow. So yeah, I
think that was that'd be what I would
tell myself out of college.
>> Awesome. Well, thanks so much for your
time, Stefan. I was really looking
forward to talking to you and kind of
digging into all this management stuff.
So,
>> well, thank you for for having me. I
guess for Hello Interview, if you are at
a uh kind of a lead tech company and and
interested in in helping us out with
coaching people through the interview
process and basically making the process
less painful for engineers, which is,
you know, generally speaking what we're
we're after. Uh we'd love to hear from
you. So if you work at OpenAI or
Anthropic or Meta or Google and you want
to help us out by working with
candidates, send us an email. My email
is stefanhello.com.
Um, and happy to kind of brief you on
what we're building and how you might be
able to help.
>> Hey, thanks for watching the show. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to support, you can
subscribe on YouTube or you can leave a
review on Spotify. And I'm always
looking for new guests to interview. So,
if anyone comes up who you think you
really want to hear their career story,
uh, let me know and I'll try to reach
out to them and get them on the show.
Thanks for listening as always and I'll
see you next time.